#### Gaurav Kalra

(415) 606-3592 ■ gkalra2002@yahoo.com ■ LinkedIn

## PROFILE SUMMARY

Software Architect with extensive experience (19 years) in enterprise product development, creating custom frameworks that aid in quick delivery of products for deployment in cloud environments. Proven success in collaborating with engineering, product management, architecture, support and customers to help customers run and scale their business run in the cloud 24/7. Demonstrated track record in delivering features that involved complex data manipulation which runs on native cloud infrastructure within a distributed environment that can be monitored, scaled and executed in secured containers.

Have been involved in some very high visibility projects for executive management to build automated tooling, translation and architecture of technical rewrites and migration of old legacy code to run on modern frameworks saving the project millions of dollars over the years.

## **WORK EXPERIENCE**

Oracle Inc. Nov 2008 – Sep 2022

Software Architect

- Lead the effort to write a ANTLR parser for processing and translating legacy 10 million lines of Cobol code to Java which
  caused the product to be cheaper for customers to afford and thereby Oracle to sell more due to reduction in third party
  license investment. From a maintenance perspective, this also helped the product be more upto date in terms of
  technology stack and easier to maintain.
- Heavily involved in various stages of Cobol to Java translation automated pipeline (preprocessing, instrumenting, gathering, storing and verifying cobol with the corresponding translated Java code execution line by line).
- Adapt existing premise architecture to deployment in cloud for highly scalable, distributed components that are fault taulerant and maintainable via CI/CD pipelines.
- Responsible for analyzing, designing, developing, troubleshooting and debuging software modules that are deployed in the Oracle Cloud to ensure new customers can quickly migrate to Oracle Cloud from an On-Prem environment.
- Was able to quickly switch over from premise side development to cloud side development to support delivery of key
  modules like ORDS. While leading this effort, it was the first demonstration of hosting the ORDS product in the cloud
  which was originally meant for on-prem setup.
- Responsible for ensuring distributed components are fault taulerant for highly scalable deployment in cloud and are maintainable via CI/CD pipelines.
- Over the years have been responsible for building and designing internal development tools that helps other developers improve their velocity.
- For couple of years was leading the security effort by acting as the security point of contact for the product. Key
  responsibilities included, validating any CVE that were raised for thirdy party libraries and evaluating whether the product
  was exposed or not. This utilized making judgements based on the threat and evaluating the scans to take corrective
  actions. Besides third party, ongoing evaluation of new features being coded for secure standards and their enforcement
  was part of my job.
- Being the senior member of the team, have been very involved with interviewing candidates for open positions in the team.
- Single handedly wrote a complete Gantt chart component from scratch in 3 weeks for monitoring and dispatching tasks after evaluating that the original Oracle product from another team was not going to scale well with the amount of data we had from a performance standpoint.
- Over the years have consistently worked and coordinated with the offshore team, devops for any ongoing customer issues or development of new features.

**Technologies**: Java Enterprise (Proprietary Framework and Architecture), Oracle Cloud, Docker, Kubernetes, Java Enterprise (J2EE), EJB, Servlets, GRPC, YAML, XML, XSLT, SAX/DOM Parsers, DTD, Xpath, XSD, ANTLR Lexer and Parser, AST, Oracle Cloud DB, Jaeger, JUnit, Mockito, Kibana, Shell Scripting, Perl, AJAX, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, Gradle, ANT, CI/CD, GitLab, Hudson, Jenkins, Eclipse, CheckStyle, Linux, GIT, Perforce, SVN, OWASP, Fortify, Sonarqube, ORDS, Oracle SQL Developer, Apache Tomcat Web Server, Oracle BEA Weblogic Application Server.

Avolent Inc. Oct 2007 – Sep 2008

Sr. Software Engineer

- Act as Lead for offshore Team members, while being heavily involved in Requirement Gathering, Design Discussions with Architecture team and Implementation of new features.
- Acted as Subject Matter Expert on various modules being a core member of the framework team.

**Technologies**: Java Enterprise (Proprietary Framework and Architecture), JDBC, Servlets, Ant, XML/XSL, AJAX, JavaScript, JUnit, JBoss Application Server, Tomcat, Oracle 10g, MS SQL Server, IBM DB2, Windows XP, Solaris, UNIX, Eclipse, Perforce.

Globallogic Inc Oct 2004 – Sep 2007

Lead Engineering

- Key member of the core Product Development team and involved in Requirement Gathering, Design Discussions with Architecture team and implementation of new features, while being the Subject Matter Expert for a large number of modules.
- Responsible for mentoring young engineers and interviewing candidates for open team positions.

**Technologies:** Java Enterprise (Proprietary Framework and Architecture), JDBC, Servlets, Ant, XML/XSL, AJAX, JavaScript, JUnit, JBoss Application Server, Tomcat, Oracle 10g, MS SQL Server, IBM DB2, Windows XP, Solaris, UNIX, Eclipse, Perforce.

Sun Microsystems Jul 2004 – Sep 2004

Member Technical Staff

Member of the core Product Packaging team and responsible for the enhancement and maintenance of the existing
proprietary framework for packaging applications to install on Windows, Unix/Linux and Solaris environments.

**Technologies**: Java, Proprietary Packaging Framework, Ant, XML, Sun One App Server, Windows XP, Solaris, Linux, Netbeans, CVS, Sun Java Enterprise Studio.

Infosys Technologies Ltd.

Jan 2003 – Jun 2004

Software Engineer

 Responsible for Design and Implementation of the new features while providing support via maintenance and bug fixing for the existing application.

Technologies: EJB, JSP, Servlets, Struts, Ant, XML, BEA Weblogic Application Server, 6.3, Oracle.

#### Tele Atlas (India) Pvt. Ltd (World leader in Digital Map solutions)

Sep 2002 - Dec 2002

Software Developer Trainee

· Responsible for the development of "Advanced Write Query" module, as part of the defect tracking system.

Technologies: Java 2, RMI, JDBC, JSP, Informix, Netscape Iplanet Server, CVS.

### **ACADEMIC PROJECTS**

#### R Systems International Limited, Noida, India

Software Trainee

Jan 2002 - Jul 2002

Responsible for writing "Demonstrator – A System for Platform Independent Demonstration over a Network", the old
man's version of the current Zoom/Team product that helps team members to collaborate with other members of the
team. This was an application that was written from scatch using Swing.

Technologies: Java 2, RMI, JDBC, Swing, Oracle.

## **EDUCATION**

- MCA (1999 2002) (Percentage: 80.5%, GPA: 4.0/5.0) University School of Studies (Main Campus), GGS Indraprastha University, Delhi
- B.Sc. (G) Computer Science (1996 1999) (Percentage: 64.5%) Maharaja Agrasen College, Delhi University, Delhi
- Diploma in Network centered computing from NIIT (Grade: A)

# **ACHIEVEMENTS, AWARDS & INTERESTS**

- Stood second in the Day Programming competition held at infoXpression 2001, Annual National Student's IT meet, organized by School Of Information Technology, GGS Indraprastha University, Delhi, India.
- Modding retro game consoles for RGB and various other mods.
- Tinkering and creating small projects with my daughter on Raspberry Pi and Arduino. Presently teaching her the C
  programming language.
- Playing Table Tennis and watching Formula 1